A Guide to the Collection of Aztec [Nahuatla]and other native Mexican language documents, ca. 1547-1906
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Collection of Aztec [Nahuatl]and other native Mexican language documents ca. 1547-1906
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10784
This collection consists of sixty-nine documents.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Central American Indian Language Collection was transferred by deed of gift to the Library on November 14, 1988, by Jefferson National Bank Administrative Officer, Frank T. Vaughn, Jr., of Charlottesville, Virginia.
Provenance
This collection was formerly part of the William E. Gates Collection.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of sixty-nine manuscripts and broadsides, ca. 1547-1906, chiefly linguistic in nature, and of a uniformly Mexican origin. The majority of documents are Aztec, a Nahuatl-speaking tribe of Indians who dominated much of Mexico at the time of the Spanish Conquest (1519-1521). Other Indian dialects in this collection include: Mazatec, Mixtec, Zapotec, Cuicatec, Chinantec, Mazahua, Oaxacan, and several unidentified dialects.
Most of these manuscripts were practical aids to parish priests in their ministry among Indians, including confesionarios, containing lists of questions, statements, responses, and vocabulary in both Spanish and the native language that a confessor might use in his work; catechisms and prayers in Spanish and the native language; doctrina, and vocabulary lists, both in Spanish and the native tongue.
Several documents are unrelated to Indian languages. These include: a petition for admission to the Real Colegio de Abogados in Mexico City (1802); a report to the Audiencia of Mexico by the King's fiscal(1779); a Special Indulgence from the Inquisitor General in Spain in favor of the Hospital in Yllescas (1602); a Special Indulgence by the Primate of Toledo to the Nuns in Oaxaca (1745); Report regarding the unlawful arrest of former U.S. Consul John Black by complaint of William Parrott (1836); Account records in Spanish for Rural laborers employed on a private estate (1884-1889); and a Diploma in the Madrid Academy of Jurisprudence and Legislation (1840).
These manuscripts were once part of a much larger collection known as the William E. Gates Collection which was sold in 1924. William Edmond Gates (1863-1940) was the President of the Maya Society, Honorary Professor of the Museo Nacional de Mexico, and a Research Associate of The Johns Hopkins University who devoted his scholarly life to researching the civilization of the Indians of Mesoamerica, especially the Mayan language.
According to Gates, "The Collection was begun twenty-five years ago [1898] with the idea of gathering and leaving as a permanent foundation for students everything possible bearing on the languages, history and archaeology of the Indian races of Middle America--particularly the Maya civilization of Guatemala and Yucatan."
Organization
The folders are arranged chronologically and each folder includes the Gates catalog number if known. The identification of the documents was derived by matching them with the description in the Gates catalog or the notes of William Taylor, University of Virginia, Department of History.
Contents List
- Central American Language Collection ca. 1547-1906, This series contains sixty-nine manuscripts and broadsides. (Box 1-2)
  The folders are arranged chronologically and each folder includes the Gates catalog number if known. The identification of the documents was derived by matching them with the description in the Gates catalog or the notes of William Taylor, University of Virginia, Department of History.
  - Partial Manuscript of the Mexican Grammar, Arte de la Lengua Mexicana and Vocabulario, by Andres de Olmos, pp. 2-7 (#761) ca. 1547 (Box 1)
  - Titulos de Coatlinchan, in the Tezcoco district, granted for assistance rendered by the cacique to Cortes; w/ description of the coat of arms, granted to Don Valeriano Francisco de Buen Dia Atutzquetzin Ixquixochitl and Don Graviel Cortez de Buen Dia Huecacahuitl, also includes other documents, such as the music for the Kyrie Eleison and a Bull of 1754 (# 759) ca. 1549-1771, 19 pp. (Box 1)
  - Tribute Manuscript in Aztec and Spanish concerning the "tributos de grana, anil y tierra parda," (# 762) 1577 January 6, 14 pp. (Box 1)
  - Document of the town of San Pedro Tlahuac Huexocalco, in Aztec, (# 758 B) 15[?], 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Special Indulgence from the Inquisitor General in Spain, in favor of the Hospital in Yllescas, signed by the Inquisitor and Others (# 1077) 1602 (Box 1)
  - Aztec Manuscript Signed (# 764) 1603 December, 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Document of Accounts, in Aztec, (# 765) 1658 March 11, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Document in Aztec and Spanish concerning land sales near Amecameca, (# 766) 1690 November 11, 6 pp. (Box 1)
  - Four Aztec Manuscripts re Business Matters (# 769) 1703-1712 (Box 1)
  - Four Aztec Letters by Native Town Officials (# 771) ca. 1710-1715 (Box 1)
  - Aztec Manuscript, w/ signatures of the Indian Town Officials, (# 770) 1710, 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Five Manuscripts in Aztec, one concerning affairs in Xochimilco (# 772) 1719-1768 (Box 1)
  - Document of the Town of Xochimilco in Aztec, verified by the Governor of Xochimilco (# 773) 1720 August 1, Contains an elaborate rubric in place of a signature, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - Special Indulgence by the Primate of Toledo, Spain, to the Nuns in Oaxaca, w/ seal (# 1105) 1745 (Box 1)
  - Aztec Grammar Manuscript, identified by Dr. Leon as in the writing of [Benaducci Lorenzo] Boturini, (# 784) ante 1751, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Draft of a Sermon in Aztec, entirely filling the back of an Illustrated Jesuit Broadside, printed at the College of San Ildefonso, Mexico (# 774) 1755 July 20 (Box 1)
  - Report to the King by a Fiscal of the Audiencia of Mexico re the neglect of some royal laws of the Recopilacion,(# 1121) 1779, 7 pp. (Box 1)
  - Confesionario, Cuicatec and Spanish (# 935) ca. 1780, Closely written in double column (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary in Mazatec and Spanish (# 941) 1796, Double column, 18 pp. (Box 1)
  - Confesionario, in Mazatec and Spanish (# 940) 1797 January 18, Double column, 35 pp. (Box 1)
  - Aztec Manuscript, Instructions for the Indians(# 789) 18th Century, 5 pp. (Box 1)
  - Aztec Manuscript (# 788 ?) 18th Century, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript with the Salve, Credo, etc. in Spanish and Zapotec (# 906) 18th Century, In parallel columns, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript in Aztec (# 786 ?) 18th Century, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Cathessismo Nathonate Manuscript, Catechism in Oaxaca dialect (# 927) 18th Century, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary, doctrina, confesionario, and prayers in Mixtec (# 915) 1800 July, Bound Volume, 148 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript Doctrina en Lengua Mizteca, Commandments and Sacraments, Four leaves Mixtec; Three leaves in Mixtec and Spanish (# 916) ca. 1800, Double columns, 14 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, Doctrina en Lengua Zapoteca, heading reads "El preambulo de la Confesion en Castellano, y en Lengua Netzicho y Caxonos," a sub-dialect of Zapotec (# 909) ca. 1800, In double column, 6 pp. (Box 1)
  - Appointment of Jose M. de la Vega as a member of the College of Attorneys, on approval of the Royal Audience, w/ an engraved seal of the Real Colegio de Escribanos (# 1136) 1802 (Box 1)
  - 2 Printed Broadsides, two columns, by the Viceroy Venegas, one in Aztec and the other with the Spanish translation, signed by Venegas and the Secretary Negrete y Soria, Granting exemption from taxation to the Indians and "loyal" mulattoes and negroes, by Royal order (# 832) 1810 October 5, Printed broadsides, in two columns (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary in Spanish and Aztec, with non-religious content (# 793 ?) 1811 June 15, 5 leaves (Box 1)
  - Catechism and Doctrine in Mazatec compiled by P. Bartolome Castano (# 943) 1820 November 30, 20 pp. (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary and Phrases in Mazatec and Spanish, pueblo de Huehuetlan (# 942) 1820, In double column, 32 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of Terms, Phrases, and Confesionarios, Spanish and Mazatec, (# 938) 1827, In double columns, 102 pp. (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary in Mazatec and Spanish (# 939) [ca. 1830], In double columns, 20 pp. (Box 1)
  - Report re the Unlawful Arrest of Former U.S. Consul John Black by Complaint of William Parrott for Slander, written in English by A. Butler (# 1147) 1836 January 20, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Confesionario, with some additional memoranda, in Chinantec, with Spanish parallel, compiled by Padre Francisco Quintero (# 930) 1838, 13 leaves (Box 1)
  - Rough Draft of a Confesionario, in Mazatec, compiled by Franciso de Paula Quintero (# 944) 1838 August 8, 26 pp. (Box 1)
  - Diploma in the Madrid Academy of Jurisprudence and Legislation (# 1150) 1840 (Box 1)
  - Checklist and Description of Manuscripts from the Biblioteca Nacional in Madrid, Works re the Indies noted in the Margin (# 1152) 1847, 135 pp. (Box 1)
    Alphabetically Arranged, w/ Reference Numbers
  - Manuscript Proclamation re the Coming of the Americans, in Aztec, w/ Spanish Translation signed by Faustino Galica Chimalpopoca (# 800) [ca. 1847], 3 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript Proclamation re the Coming of the Americans, in Aztec, w/ translation in Spanish (# 799) [ca. 1847], 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - 2 Printed Baptismal Certificates, with instructions, one in Aztec and the other in Spanish, Parish of Asuncion, Cuernavaca (# 844) 186[?] (Box 1)
  - Printed Proclamation, two columns, both Aztec and Spanish, by Domingo Bravo, announcing the restoration of the empire under Maximilian (# 833) 1863 September 23, In two columns (Box 1)
  - Printed Proclamation, in Aztec and Spanish, signed by Lic. Felipe Chiconcuautli, recalling the past glories of Montezuma's Empire and traitors, and urging support for Benito Juarez (# 834) 1866 January, 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Broadside - Printed Hymn in alternate Aztec and Spanish, in praise of the Virgin of Guadalupe, in three columns. On the verso, La Salve Regina, in Aztec, su autor F.T. Rosales (# 835) 1866 December 12, Broadside in three columns (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary in parallel columns, of Spanish and an Indian dialect "from the mountains," compiled by Manuel Marroquin 1880 December 27, In parallel columns (Box 1)
  - Account records in Spanish for rural laborers, probably employed on a hacienda or private estate 1884-1889 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of Short Vocabulary in Spanish and Mazatec (# 936) Early 19th Century, In parallel columns (Box 1)
  - Treatise in Aztec, in the writing of Faustino Chimalpopoca, on the Virgin of Guadalupe; followed by data about the descendants of Ixtilxochitl, in Spanish and Aztec (# 797) 19th Century, 5 pp. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript Vocabulary in Spanish and an Oaxaca Dialect (# 926) 19th Century, In parallel columns (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary Manuscript in Chinantec, partly in the hand of Francisco Maria de Zavaleta, but with some in a different hand (# 932) 19th Century, 14 leaves (Box 1)
  - The Lord's Prayer Manuscript in Spanish and Maczahua (# 738) 19th Century, In parallel columns, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - Confesionario in Chinantec and Spanish, in the hand of Francisco Maria de Zavaleta (# 931) 19 Century, 11 leaves (Box 1)
  - Manuscript containing phrases in Chinantec and Spanish, in parallel columns, in the hand of Francisco Maria de Zavaleta (# 929) 19th Century, 14 leaves (Box 1)
  - Manuscript in [Oaxacan] dialect, w/ questions and answers for the confessional, compiled by Antonio Maxiano (# 928) 19th Century, In parallel columns, 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - Vocabulary, in Spanish and an unidentified native dialect ca. 1905, In parallel columns (Box 1)
  - A letter in Spanish from [Cuerinero Vargh] 1906 October 20, 1 p. (Box 1)
  - A Portion of the Catalog for the William Gates Collection re Mexico and Central America, featuring the sections on linguistics and manuscripts (see control folder) 1924 (Box 2)